<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Networking Tips on Technical Book</title><link>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/</link><description>Recent content in Networking Tips on Technical Book</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>ECMP Load Balancing</title><link>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/ecmp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/ecmp/</guid><description>Intro # ECMP Hashing # ECMP is classified into per-flow load balancing and per-packet load balancing.
Per-flow load balancing can ensure the packet sequence and ensure that the same data flow is forwarded according to the routing entry with the same next hop and different data flows are forwarded according to routing entries with different next hops.
When multiple routes are installed in the routing table, a hash is used to determine which path a packet follows.</description></item><item><title>IP Precedence And TOS | DSCP</title><link>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/ip-tos-dscp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/ip-tos-dscp/</guid><description>Intro # 8 Bits of Type of Service in IP Header.
IP Precedence # RFC791/RFC1349 Interpretation
** Bits ** 7-5 IP Precedence
111 Network Control
110 Internetwork Control
101 Critic/ECP
100 Flash Override
011 Flash
010 Immediate
001 Priority
000 Routine
Bits
4 (1 = Low Delay; 0 = Normal Delay)
3 (1 = High Throughput; 0 = Normal Throughput)
2 (1 = High Reliability; 0 = Normal Reliability)</description></item><item><title>Multi Chassis Link Aggregation Basics</title><link>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/mlag/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/mlag/</guid><description>Intro # Link Aggregation Basics # Link aggregation is an ancient technology that allows you to bond multiple parallel links into a single virtual link (link aggregation group – LAG). With parallel links being replaced by a single virtual link, STP detects no loops and all the physical links can be fully utilized.
I was also told that link aggregation makes your bridged network more stable. Every link state change triggers a Topology Change Notification in spanning tree, potentially sending a large part of your network through the STP listening-learning-forwarding state diagram.</description></item><item><title>QoS</title><link>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/qos/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/qos/</guid><description>Intro # Traffic Shaping # The traffic shapers that we will look at here are commonly called token bucket shapers and are based on a token bucket algorithm which we will see can serve multiple purposes in achieving network QoS. We should note that frequently in networking literature such algorithms were also referred to as leaky bucket algorithms. In all but one case, that we will not be discussing here, these algorithms produce the same results.</description></item><item><title>Spine-leaf Architecture Basics</title><link>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/spine-leaf-arch/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/spine-leaf-arch/</guid><description>Intro # What Is Spine-leaf Architecture? # The spine-leaf architecture consists of only two layers of switches: spine and leaf switches. The spine layer consists of switches that perform routing and work as the core of the network. The leaf layer involves access switches that connect to servers, storage devices, and other end-users. This structure helps data center networks reduce hop count and reduce network latency.
In the spine-leaf architecture, each leaf switch is connected to each spine switch.</description></item><item><title>TCP Congestion Control</title><link>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/tcp-congestion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://prasenjitmanna.com/tech-book/docs/networking-tips/tcp-congestion/</guid><description>Intro # TCP is a protocol that is used to transmit information from one computer on the internet to another, and is the protocol I’ll be focused on in this post. What distinguishes TCP from other networking protocols is that it guarantees 100% transmission. This means that if you send 100kb of data from one computer to another using TCP, all 100kb will make it to the other side. This property of TCP is very powerful and is the reason that many network applications we use, such as the web and email are built on top of it.</description></item></channel></rss>